Welcome back to the second part
of the introduction to Object-Oriented Programming.
And in this lecture, we will learn about OOP
specifically in JavaScript.
So, how it's different from the more traditional OOP
and also different ways
of implementing this paradigm in JavaScript.
And don't worry, this will be a lot shorter
than the last lecture.
So, just to review.
In the last lecture, we talked about
the classical Object-Oriented Programming model
with classes and instances created from these classes.
And remember, a class is like a blueprint
which is a theoretical plan
and that we use to build many houses in the real world.
And in the same way,
the theoretical class can be used to create actual objects
which are called instances
and which we can then use in our cout.
And this process of creating an instance
is called instantiation.
Now earlier, I said that in JavaScript
things work a bit differently.
So why did I first tell you about classes and instances?
Well, it's because we do have similar concepts in JavaScript
and so it's very useful
to first understand the class instance model.
Plus, many people also just use this terminology
in the context of JavaScript.
And finally, JavaScript syntax itself
uses also some of these terms for example, instances.
And so, you really need to know
what a class is and what an instance is.
Now, anyway, how does OOP actually work in JavaScript?
Well, in JavaScript we have something called prototypes
and all objects in JavaScript
are linked to a certain prototype object.
So we say that each object has a prototype.
And now here comes the magic.
So, the prototype object contains methods and properties
that all the objects that are linked to that prototype
can access and use.
And this behavior is usually called prototypal inheritance.
So, again, prototypal inheritance means that all objects
that are linked to a certain prototype object
can use the methods and properties
that are defined on that prototype.
So basically, objects inherit methods and properties
from the prototype which is the reason why this mechanism
is called prototypal inheritance.
Just note that this inheritance is actually different
from the inheritance that we talked about
in the last lecture.
So that was one class inheriting from another class.
But in this case,
it's basically an instance inheriting from a class.
So that's very different
and so keep that in mind
or maybe in your notes.
Alright?
Now we can also say that objects delegate behavior
to the linked prototype object.
And behavior is just another term for methods here.
So besides prototypal inheritance,
we also call this mechanism, delegation.
And that's also the reason why
this arrow is pointing upwards
because technically, objects delegate their behavior
to the prototype.
On the other hand, in classical OOP with classes,
the behavior, so the methods, are actually copied
from the class to the object
and so that is completely different.
Now, I don't want you to stress out
about the exact terminology here, okay?
So I know that this is a lot of new stuff to take in,
so a lot of new words and new concepts.
But this is just to paint a very clear picture
and to give you the complete overview.
What matters to me
is that you understand how does prototypal inheritance
actually works.
Because, when we actually start using this in practice
in the next lecture,
it won't really matter
if it's called inheritance or delegation
as long as it just works as intended, right?
But since you came to this course
to learn how things actually work in JavaScript,
I'm giving you all that information here.
Even though for now it looks a little bit too much,
but am sure you will find it useful eventually.
So actually, we will come back to this diagram
and fill it with some more detail
after we have actually implemented prototypes in JavaScript.
So after you have actually see how they work in practice.
And by then, am sure that all this
will make 100% sense to you.
But anyway, we have actually already seen this mechanism
in action many times before
but without knowing that it was happening.
For example, each time that we used an array method
like map, we are able to use that method
because of prototypal inheritance.
So, when you go to MDN to check the documentation
for any array method,
what you will see there is that it's actually called
array.prototype.map.
But why is that relevant?
So, what does this mean?
Well, array.prototype is the prototype object
of all the arrays that we create in JavaScript.
So, just like this example array called num here.
Now this prototype object contains all the
array methods, including map.
So, this is where they are actually defined.
So, since array.prototype is the prototype of the
num array, it means that num is linked to that prototype.
And therefore, it has access to all the methods
that are defined on the array.prototype object,
just like the map method.
So, in a sense, our array inherits the map method.
Or again, we can also say that the array delegated
the behavior of mapping to its prototype.
So, you can choose whatever makes more sense in your mind.
But what matters, is that the map method
is actually not defined on the num array itself
but on its prototype.
And of course, we're gonna check out this behavior
also in our cout and practice,
okay?
Right now, you might have a ton of questions
in your head.
Like, how do we actually create prototypes?
And, how do we link objects to prototypes?
And how can we create new objects without having classes
from which we can instantiate objects?
So, in summary, the question is
how do we implement Object-Oriented Programming
in JavaScript in practice?
Well, in JavaScript there are actually three different ways
of doing all this: the constructor function technique,
ES6 classes and also the Object.create().
So first, constructor functions are a way
of creating objects programmatically,
using a function which will also set
the new object's prototype.
And this is actually how built-in objects like arrays
or maps or sets are implemented.
Also, this is how OOP has been done in JavaScript
basically since the beginning.
Next, the ES6 release introduced classes into JavaScript.
And so now, ES6 classes are actually the more modern way
of doing OOP in JavaScript.
However, keep in mind that these are actually
not the kind of classes that we talked about
in the last lecture and in the last slide.
They are instead just so called 'synthetic sugar'
over constructor functions.
So this means that ES6 classes are basically just
a layer of obstruction over constructor functions.
So, it's really just a nicer syntax
that makes it easier for newcomers to do OOP in JavaScript.
But behind the scenes, ES6 classes are actually implemented
with constructor functions.
And so they also use prototypal inheritance
just like we learnt in the last slide.
Finally, there's also the object.create()
which is basically the easiest and most straightforward way
of linking an object to a prototype object.
However, it's not as used as the other two methods
as we will see over the next couple of lectures.
Now, to finish, one important thing to keep in mind
is that the four principles of Object-Oriented Programming
that we learnt in the last lecture,
so that's obstruction, encapsulation, inheritance
and polymorphism are still valid and important
with prototypal inheritance.
And throughout this section,
we will of course learn how to use
and implement these principles.
Alright.
And with all that being said,
let's now finally put OOP into practice
and get a bit more technical.